foreign
[Music]
[Applause]
and live episode
two of season five Twitter files and the
death of russiagate I'm Joe Lauria the
editor-in-chief of Consortium news in
the latest installment of the
Blockbuster Twitter files reporter Matt
has revealed that probably the most
important Source behind the maniacal
media output on russiagate was based on
a lie hundreds of Articles and
television segments in the major U.S
media which kept the russiagate Fiasco
front and center in American political
life for several years was fueled by a
website called Hamilton 68.
the name comes from Alexander Hamilton's
Federalist Papers number 68 in which he
writes about the danger of foreign
interference in U.S elections Hamilton's
Hamilton Hamilton 68 was launched in
August 2017 less than a year after
Hillary Clinton's defeat to Donald Trump
and just as Democrats increasingly
blamed alleged Russian interference for
Clinton's loss as the hysteria over
unproven allegations of Russia's role
gathered steam Hamilton 68 appeared it
became a go-to source for corporate
media by saying it had a list which
refused to make public of Twitter
accounts it was monitoring
there are conflicting statements from
Hamilton about whether these were Bots
or real people whether they were direct
agents of Russia or unwitting dupes
taibi writes quote the two founders of
Hamilton 68 the blue and red team of
former councilor to Marco Rubio Jamie
fly and Hillary for America foreign
policy adviser Laura Rosenberger told
Politico they couldn't reveal the names
of the accounts because quote the
Russians will simply shut them down
Twitter the files uh that discovered say
did not buy Hamilton's story and
privately push back
the old raw food is trust and safety
Chief at the time said in one internal
email quote I think we just need to call
this out on the [__] it is
he also threatened to give Hamilton an
ultimatum either they released a list or
Twitter would
Twitter only obtained the list by
reverse engineering data requests made
by Hamilton back in 2017.
now hebe's reporting indicated these
were real people indeed only about 30
Twitter accounts on the list of 644 were
Russia the rest Real Americans britons
and Canadians
most were Trump supporters with Twitter
handles like at trumpdyke but some were
not such as myself before I became
editor-in-chief of Consortium news when
I was only a writer for this site
publishing several articles debunking
russiagate in 2017.
on Hamilton's advisory Council sits
former senior U.S officials several wood
intelligence backgrounds
such as Michael Church of former
Homeland Security director former acting
CIA Chief Michael Morrell
Rick Legend a former NSA deputy director
Clint Watts a former FBI
counterintelligence officer Mike Rogers
another former FBI agent and a member of
the U.S House intelligence committee the
former U.S ambassador to Russia Michael
mcfaul
even a former Estonian president Thomas
Ives was and John podestar
the chairman of the Clinton campaign and
Auctioneer conservative Bill Crystal
were all thrown in for good measure
Hamilton 68 has blamed the media after
tayabi's Story for misinterpreting its
data and ignoring its appeals to correct
their stories Hamilton 68 was rebranded
Hamilton 2.0 in December and its secret
list has now been replaced by a public
list that only names government
officials and media from Russia China
and Iran
we asked someone from the alliance for
securing democracy which runs Hamilton
2.0 to appear on this show and we
receive no reply
this troubling story underscores the
gross failures of corporate media like
CNN MSNBC The New York Times The
Washington Post and even fact-checking
sites like Paul at fact and Snopes
all of them was failed to be skeptical
of intelligent sources whether active or
retired it also exposes the failure of
members of Congress to not let the facts
get in the way of a story that serves
their political interests as Senators
Dianne Feinstein and Mark Warner became
reliant on Hamilton 68. Academia was
also taken in
taibi's Revelations add to a Litany of
facts that have repeatedly debunked the
Russia gay tale special counsel Robert
Mueller's report that found no
connection between Russia and the Trump
campaign the president of crowdstrike's
admission under oath Congress of finding
no evidence of any hack of the DNC
service and NYU study recently showing
minimal impact of Russian Facebook posts
and the Clinton campaign paying for both
crowdstrike and the former MI6 age at
Christopher Steele's fabulous opposition
research on Trump
the Hamilton Twitter file may at last be
the final mail in the russiagate coffee
our special guest tonight is independent
journalist Matt taibi a former reporter
for Rolling Stone magazine and an author
his latest book
is what is your latest book Matt uh hey
Dink I think this is the last one
right Matt also runs racket a sub stack
publication where his Hamilton 68 story
was published we're also joined tonight
we're happy to say so by former New York
Times correspondent and author Chris
Hedges whose latest book is the greatest
Evil news war and by John kiriako a
former CIA officer author of The
Reluctant spy and the man who blew the
whistle on the agency's torture program
thank you all three of you for joining
us tonight Matt I'm going to start with
you just tell us in your own words what
is the essence of this story what did
you learn
so Hamilton 68 as you described variably
there was basically a tool that was
designed I I think primarily to drive
narratives with the news media
um it's a it really takes a very
primitive trending technology and just
it was a hand-picked uh selection of 644
accounts that were represented to
reporters as being quote unquote linked
to Russian influence
um but actually most of them are just
sort of ordinary people uh if you go
through the list which Twitter was in a
unique position to create by reverse
engineering data requests they
engineered the list they're the only
ones apart from the the uh Hamilton 68
that has it
um they realized it was full of real
people mostly sort of low engagement
Trump supporters but also people like
you Joe and I I your your name was a big
surprise on the list
um I just went down and started clicking
all these different names and uh
basically what they were doing is
running a scam they were they were
taking opinions organic opinions of real
people and representing them as
russian-driven narratives to the news
media and this as you know birthed
um you know hundreds of news stories
I wonder if you could just clear up one
aspect of this how it worked because I
think a lot of people myself initially
not even think Glenn Greenwell when he
interviewed you last Friday said that or
thought that Hamilton was going to
Twitter to get people suspended the way
the FBI and the DHS did in your earlier
incredibly good reporting did but that
was not what happened here because they
never gave the names on the list to
Twitter Twitter how to find out on their
own isn't that right right yeah
basically
uh and some of this is lost to me
because I'm not uh technically sound
enough but basically the the chief uh
trust and security Chief Joel Roth found
uh what's called the API key
for Hamilton 68 and basically they
looked at every place the uh the think
tank was trying to access data
searchable data from Twitter about all
these accounts so every time Hamilton 68
looked up
um the tweeting history of anybody on
the list
uh Twitter knew about it and they were
basically able to reverse engineer who
was on the list by looking at all the
different requests which were basically
the same every time they were running
some kind of search on any hashtag or
anything like that
are your previous stirs on Twitter files
have been extremely extraordinarily
important in understanding how
government used a private company to try
to suppress speech to get actually
people silenced on Twitter uh but this
story is maybe of a special kind you
think this is the most important of the
Twitter file stores that you've done so
far I think
my belief is that actually this is just
sort of the beginning of a window into
so there's there's two aspects of the
digital misinformation issue that have
to be looked at one is the digital
censorship uh question which I think
most of us sort of instinctively
understood and knew was happening
um the larger question however has to do
with what they call
um offensive information operations John
might be able to tell us something about
this uh but that's when somebody is
cooking up a fake story and and pushing
it as opposed to suppressing it and this
was not just done by private actors this
was this is something that in one of Lee
Fong's earlier threads people didn't
notice it as much but it was a very
significant story about how the Pentagon
was creating fake Twitter accounts in
foreign languages overseas basically to
drive down negative chatter about things
like drone strikes so we knew they were
doing that that the Pentagon was doing
that in foreign countries but I think
we're going to find out that this is
happening in the United States we have a
few examples that are pretty ugly
already but I think we're going to learn
that it was
significantly more widespread and
Hamilton 68 was not just a think tank I
think we're going to find out that it
had
some more unnatural Origins
well that's interesting I'm going to get
to that later but when you consider the
role Russia gate has played in creating
tension with Russia starting back in
2016 and 17 and laying the groundwork in
many ways for the the war in Ukraine
right now to get the American people on
side to uh completely accept the U.S
explanation for this and reject any idea
that they provoked this war don't you
think than Hamilton's role in stirring
up that anti-russian hysteria has a
geopolitical impact and in that sense
well I thought this is maybe the most
important story
right because I mean you can look at
Hamilton 68 and say it's it's a small
organization most people never heard of
it but the larger
the larger meta story here is about the
creation of a of a very big fake story
about the Russian meddling in American
political Affairs now let's be clear
they do Russians do have information
operations they do do this they do try
to insert uh certain kinds of themes
into uh organic social media chatter but
it's nowhere near on the scale that's
been represented to Americans and there
was this enormous hysteria that was
whipped up about an essentially
fictional
um story
and that's on I I can't think of a
parallel in American history where
that's happened I mean you can maybe
call McCarthyism like that but the the
difference is that because of social
media because of everybody's so online
all the time they were able to amplify
the story uh fake stories much more
effectively and much more broadly than I
think uh ever done previously
I'm Matt what did you think of
Hamilton's response they wouldn't talk
to you before you published your piece
you gave them ample opportunity to do so
but they did right after it come out
with this fact sheet and they seem to be
blaming the media again we tried to
correct them they went too far but what
we were saying that's not what we meant
uh that they're pleading and uh you know
I mean it's uh did they and and what do
you think of that and did they know that
you were working on this story in
December and I asked that because that's
when they rebranded this thing 2.0 and
put out a public list did they know in
December that you were gonna you were
gonna get it
uh I think they have I think they had to
guess in December
um have you contacted them for comments
or in December no no I I contacted them
in January but uh I would say Earl
earliest January
um but they had to know they have ways
of finding out don't they
um
they had they had as soon as they saw
that we were looking through Twitter's
emails they must have known because they
this was actually a big deal within the
company there were there was a
significant argument between Twitter and
all the actors involved here
um I haven't uh flushed out the full
details of this but there was a lot of
back and forth there were in-person
meetings
um and so uh they had to know that if we
were looking around in the stuff that we
would see the footprint of it pretty
soon and that that's what happened we
saw it relatively quickly uh and it it's
a big deal because it's essentially a
conflict between a big private company
in Twitter and really the Democratic
party establishment and the intelligence
Community uh and that they had a they
had a real fight about this and
um but it was all suppressed
I'm gonna get that out with John the
intelligence side of it and Chris the
journalistic side of that but we're
going to stick with you for a moment
Matt I'm going to bring in my co-host
Elizabeth boss uh Elizabeth to take over
your question of Matt police sure Matt
thanks again for you know coming on and
being with us I just wanted to know are
you satisfied with how the Twitter files
have been disseminated are you good with
it being disseminated on the you know
Twitter platform do you think publishing
it via an organization like Wikileaks
would have made it more accessible to
people to look through and find their
find the stories themselves what do you
think about all that
so I was very skeptical about first of
all the format of Twitter at first
um you know the the two conditions that
I agreed to with the story were an
attribution right sources at Twitter and
the other one was that the story had to
all the BR the breaking stuff had to
come out on Twitter first and I think
you can imagine what the motives are for
that right there are several
um and that was very skeptical of this
at first I mean I'm a long-form writer
uh as I think you know everybody on on
the panel can understand it's a
difficult thing to Think Through uh in
terms of the way the story landed though
however I quickly realized that it had
to be on Twitter like it it made a lot
of sense in both from a PR standpoint
and there's an irony in it too right
because you're using Twitter to Flay
Twitter
um Twitter was originally kind of a an
Arctic or organization that was
essentially destabilizing right and the
the plot that we're looking at is
government's attempt to turn that around
and turn Twitter into a a tool of
control so there's an irony of using
Twitter to turn the tables again I
understand the call to release
everything but like this this story is
an example of why that made me nervous
in addition to all the other things
about the story that make me nervous
like what happens if I release all these
644 names and there are eight of them
who have negative consequences because
they're now identified somewhere as
Russian Bots publicly right so that's
kind of the same dilemma you have with
stuff like Wikileaks like you want to
look through it first and then I I think
I think at some point something like
that will happen but I I can't I can't
speak to that it's not my company but I
understand the thinking on both sides of
that question
sure and during Russia gate we saw Jill
Stein Tulsi gabbard and so many others
falsely smeared as Russian agents you
know we've had them blamed in Tulsi
gabbard's case in part for Hillary
Clinton losing on and on will there ever
be a real Reckoning for this and all of
these lies
well I think this week uh it's a good
time to talk about this the Columbia
journalism review this week dropped a 26
000 word excoriation of the news media
written by as credentialed and down in
the middle a mainstream reporter as as
you can get Jeff girth who is a veteran
of New York Times for many years
um Chris I don't know if you know knew
him well but uh it's just the gigantic
compendium of errors and the response
has been absolutely nothing so if you if
you drop something a book length thing
on the Columbia journalism review and
you can't get a 30-second hit on CNN out
of that
I mean I I don't I don't think we're
getting the Reckoning voluntarily let's
put it that way
yeah I mean just looking up the Twitter
files looking up Hamilton 68 you get so
few search results whether it's on
YouTube Google wherever there's a couple
of uh you know of stories it's almost
nothing uh you know and obviously as
that uh Columbia journalism review uh
long long uh series of Articles States
basically the US's uh Public's trust in
the media has just been completely
damaged in this era
um I just you know I want your comments
on that and whether that will ever be
repaired if it can be
well I think this is something that uh
Chris and I have talked about before
um
so the obvious solution the the news
media business is in crisis financially
and from kind of a a psychic meta
standpoint like their their relationship
to our audiences is very confused and
and very troubled right now and the
obvious solution for them is to start
doing their jobs
and they cannot bring themselves to do
it it would be both a financial solution
and a moral solution and they they can't
do it I don't I don't fully understand
that that situation because there have
to be some self-interested companies
Chris I'd be really curious to hear what
you think about this
um why there aren't a few organizations
who have said you know this isn't
working for us we get we gotta step off
and start doing the right thing and they
won't do it
um I think that would be an interesting
thing to discuss actually
Chris do you want to answer that
you're muted still
there can you hear me so look at uh
Louis manan's
uh article in the New Yorker when
Americans lost faith in the news
and it's just uh
this diatribe against the right wing and
Trump
for tarrying the news as the enemy of
the people there's zero introspection I
mean I worked at the New York Times
there's That's a classic institution
that doesn't have the capacity to engage
in any self-criticism it's kind of
Byzantine uh and and dismisses everybody
outside the walls of the New York Times
is kind of uh you know second-rate
journalists and second rate
uh thinkers and second rage citizens I
mean there's the air I think a lot of it
is hubris a lot of it is because they
all talk to each other they're all
having dinner with the editors of the
intercept and The New Yorker and they
you know they kind of it's a mutual
admiration society which is of course
what's destroyed The Intercept Glenn is
completely right I of course know all
those people
um so I think it's it's the I think it's
a mixture of hubris and a mixture of uh
and uh a kind of uh feeling that any
kind of critique or outside attack is
uh from the very start not valid and I I
you know I covered I was overseas for
many years in the Middle East and in
Latin America so I the paper was roundly
attacked and often uh deserved to be
attacked
um but it it had uh in the inner sanctum
of the New York Times it had almost no
effect unless that attack came from
moneyed or interests or powerful
interests so
um uh but but leftist critics uh
independent journalists you know anybody
who tried to call them out were just
dismissed and so the more anemic these
news organizations become and
financially of course they're becoming
more anemic uh the more insular I think
they become and the more uh they
essentially accelerate their own demise
I think that's what's happened I mean
also having to confront what Matt
exposed uh
it's not just one or two articles we're
talking about hundreds if not thousands
of Articles we're talking about the
tenor of reporting day after day week
after week and to confront that complete
failure uh it I think is so massive uh
that it it uh would just rock the
foundations of whatever news industry
that had the honesty to go back and be
straight with either their viewers or
their readers uh and they're just
they're not going to do it I mean that's
why the two things they'll do is ignore
it and hope it goes away and and anytime
they write about Matt taibi
um they'll you know and they'll have
some snide adjective to describe him
it's kind of funny because uh not to
interject but but
it's like fighting with somebody who
won't who won't punch back they seem to
be in of this belief that this is going
to go away
um but there's more of this stuff coming
I mean it's just gonna get worse uh so I
mean and it's not just gonna come for me
it's going to come from all kinds of
people as we're finding out so it seems
like a
if they're going to have to get the
message eventually somebody is going to
have to break ranks I think it won't be
the New York Times because they have no
accountability mechanism left at all at
that newspaper I don't think but I would
think a smaller organization would at
some point
uh Chris you spent probably happily most
of your time off of that Island in New
York or out of The Newsroom as a foreign
correspondent but what's troubling here
what Matt's story really points out is
on this insular uh click here of the top
editors and the newspaper themselves are
government officials intelligence
officials in particular they're included
in this little click in a way in terms
of the fact that whatever a U.S former
or active intelligence official says is
almost instantly believed without any
checking without any skepticism it
becomes a conduit a laundry a laundering
of intelligence that would otherwise
probably not be believed by the American
people but it comes under the name of
the New York Times it might be more
believable what's going on here in the
mentality of people in the press that
they are so uh servile to members
that's not new I mean that's that I know
that but this story really points it out
in a big way
well sure so did the weapons of mass
destruction I mean I was in Paris right
that was part of that team and I was
working French intelligence opened up
everything to me because they wanted to
avoid the war in Iraq so I had carp
launch I mean I covered Richard Reed the
shoe bomber I would go down to the
counterterrorism ministry run by this
crazy Corsican and uh and and it was
like snapping your fingers and next
thing I'd have a pile of all the French
Intelligence on Richard Reed including
some balanced photos of him coming out
of the bricks that moth everything
and uh it was this desperate attempt it
was only because I was with the New York
Times not because I was a great reporter
but it was this desperate attempt to
essentially use the times as a conduit
uh to make it clear that Saddam Hussein
had no weapons of mass destruction and
no connections to Al-Qaeda or anything
else and I would periodically fly back
to New York in that investigative
meeting and and bring hard intelligence
and it was just laughed at because they
were all going down to Washington and
having uh lunch with Lewis scooter Libby
and Dick Cheney and Richard Pearl and
everyone else and it was arrogance it
was just all the French you know so
that's long been the case I mean the
there's long been very incestuous
relationship between intelligence
agencies in the New York Times that
that's nothing new
what's that
I would just say the new wrinkle is that
they're physically replacing journalists
now with with intelligence people I mean
the the the roster of x uh CIA NSA FBI
whatever John with all due respect uh
you know everyone from Brennan to Clint
watts to Asher and gapa to I mean uh
they all have media jobs now uh and the
real reporters are being cycled out and
these big contracts are being given to
X intelligence officials as if it's the
same job and as we all know it's the
opposite job intelligence intelligence
is about deception I mean in some in
most circumstances right uh in
journalism that you're supposed to do
the other thing and they think for some
reason that it's it's authoritative but
it's not uh really yeah I mean that but
that's Electronic media I don't you know
the times isn't doing that I mean
they'll quote these people with
reverence of course I have a few um uh
but it I think I I don't think that
journalism is that's kind of the last
thing that MSNBC or CNN is doing it's
about ratings it's about entertainment
it's about catering to a particular
demographic I think you're both hate and
could kind of you know talked about
those silos and what they're doing and
you'd never you never pay for when
you're wrong because you're telling your
demographic what it is they want to hear
so I I mean I come out of the Middle
East was appalled at this podcast that
was on the New York Times called the
caliphate which you know the first 10
minutes I realized it was garbage I mean
it was just completely ridiculous it was
kind of almost pornographic you know I
mean it just didn't ring true from
anybody who come out of the Middle East
well they never paid a price so they
didn't even fire the reporter who she
was she was it was all based on one
character who was you know completely
lying about everything but but it's what
people wanted to hear about Muslims so
they never paid a price for that they
don't they you know they as long as they
CA it's when they go against their
demographic that they pay a price
so uh I'm I'm a little more skeptical
than you are I think you know all of
these institutions that slog this
russiagate stuff one because it's so
massive I think they they would look
ridiculous if they were honest about the
level of deception that they engaged in
but secondly their demographic doesn't
want to hear it uh I mean this New
Yorker piece talks about Julian Assange
as a Russian agent I mean if Anna calls
him a criminal I mean
um but it's kind of an amazing piece but
it's a good window into how distorted
the mindset of mainstream journalism
has become and
I hope you're right but I I I I I
on second thought I doubt it I mean
tell if it's the story I'd forgotten
about that but I mean what was the story
in the in the Washington Post in the 80s
where there was like it was a fabulism
situation where some columnist invented
a fake uh tale of a I think it was a
street orphan or something like that
yeah yeah yeah yeah it was a young woman
reporter right right and it was it was
unbelievably notorious right it was
reputation shaking for the post it just
sort of rippled throughout the entire
business that was like a pimple compared
to the caliphate thing I mean it's not
even close to the scale and there's just
not no recognition of the that you know
that was a awesome scale uh case of
fabulism and and they don't even talk
about it no I don't think they're going
to talk about it I I think
because I think if they if they actually
had to confront it with any honesty it
would it would it would just rip the
whole foundations out of their
Enterprise and because we're talking
about years of reporting we're talking
about hundreds if not thousands of
stories uh that were just based on this
fraud uh and it uh
uh it wrote what is it was the famous we
used to run errors
oh I can't remember I forgot but I would
I remember being the New York Times
there were just some errors were so
embarrassing they couldn't run them they
just didn't put them in the error box
when this is just a gigantic fill up
pages of air you know Pages pages of the
newspapers with Mia culpas uh so I mean
I think what was this 2017 yeah I think
why this is so important what you've
exposed is that it it it it really
challenges the entire ethic the entire
structure of
the mainstream media which is why I
would be highly surprised if
any of them touched it
let me bring John kiriako in here uh
John I want your thoughts but I'd start
you off with a question and then I want
you guys to continue just having a free
discussion
um
as I described a lot of the people on
The Advisory Board a very senior former
intelligence officials former CIA active
CI director head of Homeland Security uh
deputy director of the NSA now in David
Talbot's book The Devil's chess board he
describes how Alan Dulles set up
um in his Georgetown townhouse a kind of
Rogue intelligence operation after he'd
been fired by John Kennedy he was no
longer the director of the CIA but he
had this operation going out of his
house with active agents working for him
my from your experience what do you know
about the kinds of relationships that
former senior intelligence high level
senior intelligence officials have with
active members of the intelligence
community
well I Joe I'll answer that question
with uh with a short anecdote all right
my last headquarters job at C at CIA was
I was the executive assistant to the
deputy director for
um sorry the associate deputy director
for operations
and so I had a fabulous office
comfortable furniture and a secretary so
I was leaning back in my chair one day
in the middle of the afternoon and I had
direct line of sight into the hallway
and as I was leaning back I saw Bob
Woodward walk past the office without a
security escort just walking around like
he owned the place
and I said to the secretary was that Bob
Woodward I just saw walk past the office
and she said yeah
I said without a security expert er uh
escort Bob Woodward just walking around
and she said oh didn't you see the
director's memo
he's writing a book about the Iraq War
and we've all been ordered to cooperate
with him
and that just encapsulated the change in
the cia's attitude toward the media
because they came to the to the
realization I guess or to the point
where they felt that they controlled the
media they owned the media
why not let Bob Woodward walk around
like he owned the place he's going to
write exactly what you tell him to write
and then when you the director or the
deputy director decide to move on and to
retire you can call Bob Woodward or his
bosses at the Washington Post and
arrange your next Golden parachute now
it's CNN and MSNBC and the college that
you got your grad degree uh in and
they'll put you on the board I mean it's
uh
it's it's a a life now it's a
post-agency life that was just
Unthinkable 20 years ago or 25 years ago
yeah let me just let me just interject
there because there's two types of
reporters I mean I was overseas so I was
in Iraq
I was on the ground in El Salvador
you're right Bob Woodward is just a
court here he he he he writes you know
he's
it's like a courtier at Versailles uh
who is given special access because he
writes you know the garbage they give
him uh which makes for good narrative
and most of which is either highly
edited or false I mean the famous story
about after the attack of 9 11 somebody
in the White House typed up a whole
dialogue in The Situation Room
supposedly by George W bush that we
found out later was completely
fictitious but Woodward slapped it into
his book so those of us who are overseas
were constantly battling not only
I mean I had a personal war with Sandy
Berger who was head of
Clinton's National Security uh
I mean he loathed me when I was in in
and made my life miserable in Yugoslavia
but so it's not only a war with figures
like that but it's also a war with
reporters who are the majority out of
paper like the New York Times but the
Bob Woodwards all these people who do
lunch in Washington all these people who
can walk without escorts through the CIA
and
um and that really wears you down if
you're an honest reporter so my whole
career was was a fight uh not only
against you know uh
mendacious and malicious power
structures
but also within the own your own
institution they always get you in the
end
so dick Holbrook
who didn't like his own go to the
details as to why but I mean it was
after Dayton and the warlord still ran
everything and I got a was leaked by the
Swiss foreign minister an osce report
that said you can't have free elections
Clinton was running for reelection this
was and I published this report which
they went berserk but then they went
they went after me and so they dick
Holbrook was tasked with taking the
publisher out to lunch and defaming me
and and it works it works it worked with
Sydney schanberg it worked with David
alberstam I worked with Ray Bonner works
with any any they always get you in the
end always uh and uh and so I I don't
want to take away from what John said
he's exactly right but there are there
were those of us on the ground who tried
but in the end we're almost always
defeated
hey I'd like to add something to that
too
um
Jason Leopold uh who's now with
Bloomberg uh and does a lot of
Freedom of Information Act requests did
one several years ago in which he asked
very simply for all Communications
between the cia's office of public
affairs and uh any journalist from
one date to the next date and what he
found was was this unseemly cooperation
between the CIA and
and journalists that are supposed to be
reporting on National Security here in
Washington the worst offender in that
tranche of of documents was kendallenian
formerly of the Los Angeles Times now of
NBC MSNBC where delanian was actually
sending his pieces to the CIA for their
clearance before sending them to his own
editor
well that's not National Security
journalism that's essentially doing what
uh what Bob Woodward has always done for
whomever happens to be sitting in the in
the White House there were other but the
problem is that if you don't do that in
Washington they shut you out you cut you
off exactly and that was that that was
the next sentence that was going to come
out of my mouth there were actual
threats
from the CIA to some of these
journalists that they wouldn't be
invited to the CIA Christmas party
seriously that they wouldn't
um have access to to the leaks that the
CIA was so famous for
and invariably they back down
that's
Washington that's how Washington works
and yeah the Washington beer the
Washington Bureau of the New York Times
is an utter cesspool where they were
Kundalini on their knees did ham 68
stories so um of course he did uh
you know I have a question from Matt uh
Joe if you don't mind oh go ahead one of
the things that has really struck me
Matt and I I like deep down I know I
shouldn't be surprised by this but it's
how you're being beaten about the face
and head by people who uh purport to be
progressives uh they've accused you
they've accused Glenn Greenwald and
others of being
um closet right Wingers because you're
not buying into the narrative the
discredited Narrative of of russiagate
and I'm wondering how you deal with that
because you're clearly not a closet
right winger you're a journalist who's
following the story where the evidence
is leading you but how do you respond to
that
um I respond to that with
boundless rage and thirst for Revenge
which I'm now getting uh and the look my
career was uh altered uh
definitively by the story there's no
question in my mind if Russia gate never
happened I would still beat rolling
stone
um I would still be writing stories
about Wall Street I would
uh basically have the same career that
I'd had for 15 years leading up to the
story my problem I was set at the
beginning of the Trump years I was going
to do a basically every month catalog of
the whole history like a Herodotus like
history of the Trump years and I did if
you go back and look you'll see I did
one installment it's actually behind me
the the tornado on the wall there
um Trump the Destroyer but because of
the Russia angle I couldn't do the story
I I we we quickly realized that this was
unreportable for our audience because I
had too many questions about the stuff
that people like Amy Klobuchar were
saying on the senate floor about Trump I
I would go back to editors and I would
say this doesn't scan that doesn't scan
I went to Adam schiff's office I asked
where did they get this did they check
this no right how do I report this right
like it's it's not true or it's it's not
reliable
and so you know that that was the first
moment that started me down the road of
leaving the magazine
um that also came with an avalanche of
social media invective I think we've all
gone through this
um it was very nasty in my case uh in a
lot of ways but all the reporters who
who didn't go along went through this it
was very personally upsetting we lost
friends we were frozen out
um you know probably 95 percent of the
people that were in my Rolodex in 2016
would not speak to me during the Trump
years at all like I couldn't pick up the
phone uh former good sources of mine uh
completely ghosted me and I was just I
mean I I was just doing my job like
I was not like uh a crusader on this
issue
um for a long time I I just felt like
God would sort of gently do a column
about how hey maybe we should reconsider
some of these facts and I don't know
I'll be curious to hear what everybody
else's experiences because
I it was totally different than anything
else I had ever dealt with before in
public life
um the the response was so
disproportionate and and crazy
um but I think you know they they
created a lot of enemies and motivation
for people in this process so I don't
know
well I I would say that that that's kind
of the trajectory of any good reporter
it ends you end up being pretty lonely
I mean because you're sorry right I mean
that's kind of it I mean uh whether it's
high of stone or Seymour Irish or I mean
all the people you and I respect
I mean look what they've done to Seymour
he can't even publish in the United
States anymore
right I would say that if you and I
would I would add Julian Assange to that
and you know if you really do your job
you know it's it's uh I mean I went
through it overseas I mean the you know
the for instance in Kosovo
I rigorously reported on Serb atrocities
against Kosovo albanians and uh and uh
you know they loved me and then the
moments the serbs left I
you know I I uh my job as a journalist
is to report on those people who are
being persecuted or don't have a voice
or vulnerable all I did was write about
the uh kosovar albanians attacking
ethnic serbs
and I instantly became persona non Greta
uh uh in a big way uh and uh and I think
that that's you know that's Orwell I
mean that's any any great any serious
like Matt I will hold in very high
esteem I mean any serious journalist in
the end is going to alienate all sorts
of people who aren't interested in
honesty and aren't interested in any
kind of
uh
uh you know investigations that disrupt
their particular world view or ideology
so you know I I'm not going to go
through the trajectory of my own career
but I think that's
I mean part of the way I deal with it
unlike Matt and Glenn I don't have a
Twitter account I'm not on so I don't
have a Facebook account on Instagram I
don't even own a television uh and it
gets kind of really good for my mental
health maybe we'll call up and say you
know what they and I don't actually know
I don't really I mean I used to be a big
Target for aipac and I would like Matt
to when he has time to look at the hand
of the Israel Lobby there because all of
us who have been outspoken against
Palestinian rights and supporters of BDS
have been targeted relentlessly by aipac
and I'm curious as to whether you know
they had any kind of I I'm I would think
they had a d platforming program uh
towards Palestinian activists and would
be my guess
um uh so
uh you know I think I think Matt's you
know paying the price for being a good
journalist and and going to get better
um
on the Palestinian front uh
the first story I did about the internet
censorship which I thought was a big
deal that was that was another sort of
disillusioning moment because I I
thought this was a big thing and nobody
else in the business seemed to think it
was but
um one of the things that you learn is
that the Palestinians are like sort of
the the test subjects for every new
digital uh censorship tool
um every time they come up with
something new
to do what Twitter called visibility
filtering right
um whether it's Trends blacklisting
search blacklisting whatever it is
um they would do it to Palestinian
accounts first the Facebook did all
kinds of things with
um the Mossad uh they had a sort of an
open Arrangement there uh to censor
because Facebook is basically the it was
the press for uh in in Palestine as far
as I understood
um so yeah there's I'm sure there's
something there and if I I just haven't
seen it talked about because probably
they they found a way to algorithmically
squash the Palestinians so long ago that
it's it's before the chair that I'm
looking at
um but it's probably in there somewhere
John if I could ask you a question
um
this seems to me to be an intelligence
operation the Hamilton 68. it's only
fronted by Former Intelligence what kind
of relations do they have to current is
I mean we don't have any proof obviously
but what is your speculation about
whether this was linked to people who
are actually still serving they can't be
on a board like this they can't be seen
to be involved in any of this but
they've got these former people who are
now private citizens
so I just want to know if you can weigh
in on that idea
sure all former directors Deputy
directors and Associate Deputy directors
maintain their security clearances in
perpetuity
um all of them are welcome to go back to
headquarters whenever they want they are
allowed classified briefings
not top secret but up to the secret
level
they have
free access to the director's private
dining room uh in fact I I've seen them
meeting in uh in the dining room with
journalists over the years
so you know there's that there's that
tired old saying that
that most people who are at the CIA
never really leave the CIA at that
senior level that's true because after
30 years or 25 years all of your
contacts are in the intelligence
Community everybody's looking to make a
lot of money when they leave
and they're looking to do something new
nobody wants to make his way over to
Booz Allen and be yet another former
senior Cia person at Booz Allen there
are a million of them there they want to
do something bigger and more lucrative
and I think that's why we're seeing
these groups like Hamilton 68 pop up or
or these anti this group that uh that
gave a red check mark to uh Consortium
news the Name Escapes me already
um
what's it called
oh
yeah News Guard yeah they want to do
something new and and big and more
lucrative let the let the lower level
guys end up at Booze Allen or at abraxis
Corporation or wherever it is that they
go now so yeah I I even though they all
have former in front of their titles now
to me that doesn't really mean anything
because they have as much access
at least to people as they ever had you
know
sorry there's a polar political agenda
here though it wasn't just about making
money I like to ask you might have
absolutely they make money this was an
agenda to
to smear Trump Wikileaks Russia and set
the stage for the crisis we've got now I
think in many ways well there there was
a perfect storm that took place you know
going back a little bit further what
what made John Brennan somebody I listen
I worked for John Brennan when he was a
gs-14 nobody
and um and what made him somebody was a
a deep friendship with George Tenet and
then when it was time to retire and move
on to something else and everybody was
going either to the Hillary Clinton
campaign or to the John McCain campaign
he was literally the only
senior Cia retiree that went to the
Obama campaign
and that made him somebody
uh he decided that he could turn that
into something even bigger
by then going to the media when he was
done you know John used to tell
everybody who would listen that he
wanted to be Secretary of Defense under
the next Democratic president well why
why would you want to make two hundred
thousand dollars as Secretary of Defense
which would then put you into your 70s
when you can spend those years at MSNBC
making
10 times
which you would have made at the at the
Pentagon
and then when people saw
him making money and and uh
uh what's his name the former dni making
money and every former four-star Clapper
thank you every former four-star general
is a talking head for CNN
you know
and you've got these Democratic
credentials because you loyally
Faithfully served Barack Obama for six
years or eight years whatever it was
why not run with it and you know the the
other thing too Joe is these guys are
very very mainstream
they're very DNC there's nothing that's
going to carry them out of the
mainstream and if the mainstream is
telling them
that to beat Donald Trump you have to
chat up this DNC plan to convince the
American people that the first thing
Donald Trump does in the morning when he
wakes up is he calls his Russian Handler
to get his his marching orders for the
day
then that's what you do
it's worked for them
isn't that a whole story so funny can
you imagine Donald Trump having the
opsec to keep that secret
it's just
a cousin of mine who's very much a DNC
you know mover and Shaker set me up
um with a with a woman who's an attorney
at the DNC lovely lovely woman and we
went out for one date and through the
entire date all she talked about was how
the Russians controlled Donald Trump and
I said I said you don't really believe
that though deep down I mean at the CIA
if there was one thing I took out of my
CIA uh career especially from the
analytics side it's that if you're gonna
say something you absolutely have to
have the information to back it up you
have to have the facts you can't just
throw a grenade into the middle of the
room and expect everybody to salute it
you have to back it up
and she said to me I believe in my heart
that Donald Trump does exactly what
Vladimir Putin tells him to do
and you know I I realize there's no
sense in carrying on the conversation
any longer
because they really believed that at the
DNC maybe not at that top level that had
come up with the big lie
but everybody else who was there to
implement it they believed it
you know the problem is you have a bunch
of analysts sitting around the CIA
dreaming up all sorts of garbage uh you
know when they actually need to drag out
the Cardinal and Prague who's been sleep
deprived for three weeks and he looks
like a zombie the CIA suddenly decides
the Soviets have figured out forms of
mind control and then sends Stanley
Gottlieb off to along with a you know
hundreds of ex-nazis to Black sites to
and I mean and then they're giving LSD
to even their own agents or jumping out
of Windows I mean uh oh you read my
piece in Consortium news no no I read uh
kinsler's book I read kinsler's book
Poison or in Chief but but it's uh
you know I mean I know overseas they
they would come and the other thing is
that the I mean as you know there's two
types of CIA there's the guys who come
out of the special forces and know how
to put explosives under trucks and blow
them up and uh those guys as soon as you
walk in the room you know they work for
and then there's the guys who went I had
a friend you know clearly CIA had done
his PhD in Princeton on vogeland and we
used to have long dinners talking about
vogeland a Charming guy Cuban American
in Central America
um but they get these theories I mean
like for instance when Huntington's book
came out Clash of civilizations they
just it was it was a it's a ridiculous
premise just it doesn't even make any
sense when you for instance you know
really know the Middle East uh but uh
that it gave them the kind of shorthand
or the slogans or the cliches that they
hung their ideology on uh I mean that
was my experience with I mean you know
I and especially in Salvador we dealt a
lot with them about 60 percent of the
embassy was had the same we got the
embassy
uh phone list and 60 had exactly the
same extension now we had the deputy
head of The Phoenix Program there I mean
we had all these guys there I mean they
were just swarming all over El Salvador
didn't speak Spanish they'd all been in
Vietnam you know what the [__] they were
doing that sitting the Sheridan with
their Vietnamese wives and uh well the
funny story is I'm in Bosnia in and I S
and I hear this guy across the room go
hola combinero and it was one of these
Cuban Americans I'm going what the hell
is he doing we had Felix Rodriguez there
well we all knew it used to show us the
wristwatch he'd taken off Che guevara's
body
um so
yeah yeah I mean that again I mean you
know it better than I do but it's an
it's also a very insular world where you
know like the New York Times where these
people feed off of each other and it can
go and really
absolutely bizarre directions but you
know that's that's my kind of you know
having been on the periphery of it that
was my take
it sounds like you you had them pegged
I have to say the CIA saved my life
though twice once once in El Salvador
when the death squads were gonna come
and kill me and not that they like me
but they showed up with an armored car
and said you got to leave right now
don't even pack your bag
and they flew me to Costa Rica and the
second time was when I was a prisoner in
Iraq and it being the New York Times
They got the pope to call Tariq Aziz who
was Christian and on my behalf they got
Schwarzkopf to call the head of the
Iraqi army they got Gorbachev to call
Saddam Hussein and I after the war I had
to write thank you notes to All these
people and then I had to write one to
the CIA but I don't know what they did
but I had to write them a thank you note
Johnston
something you were saying John uh it
reminded me of just the experience of
trump derangement syndrome in general
during the whole retrogate era I mean so
this Hamilton 68 this labeling of
American citizens and other you know
ordinary people's views and expressions
of opinion as disinformation as a
Russian Bots it was just at this
hysterical pitch and I think as Matt was
also mentioning earlier it was something
that everybody experienced on kind of
like the journalist side of it but then
as you say John like when you talk to
people who really believed it it was
like a religious fervor they had about
it so I just wanted to you know ask you
all kind of about your experience of
trump Arrangement syndrome or what you
know that hysteria during the Russia era
and if that was unique I mean or if you
think this is it'll play out the same
way again on the next kind of saga the
next moral not moral panic but the next
equivalent narrative that the media
really pushes
any of you John mad anybody
I definitely may I say real quickly
um
I I was at the Venezuelan Embassy the
night that uh that it was ordered closed
uh and uh as I was leaving with most
everybody else some some elected to stay
inside
um I overheard two uniformed Secret
Service
um officers talking one of them said so
who are these people
and the other one said the ones out here
with us
the ones inside are with Putin
um and the other one kind of chuckled
and the second one said no seriously
it's like with Trump
and you know just to hear something like
that and to realize that they that they
mean it that
you know your initial reaction is you
think wow what a couple of simpletons
and then you realize no it's not that
they're simpletons it's that they've
been exposed to this propaganda for so
long this this unrelenting reporting
that that Donald Trump is a Russian
agent and that the Russians have
controlled our elections listen there's
a guy that I used to work with at the
CIA we work together desk to desk for
years and now I just read in the
Washington Post a couple of weeks ago he
was named to head the new office of
election Integrity in the office of the
Director of National Intelligence like
Integrity for what
we've already proven that the Russians
didn't have any impact in our elections
but people really believe that they just
refuse to look at the evidence that's
placed before them we need more
reporting from the likes of Matt taibi
to to prove to the American people that
they're just simply mistaken they've
been duped they've been LED astray
there's no evidence to back up what
they've been told and we have to make
sure that this doesn't happen again
uh John just quickly if I could
um on that uh
so I this story as I alluded to earlier
does go in another it goes deeper
um I think the themes that are going to
emerge from this
um are that the intelligence Community
has been working
not just on controlling
uh censoring people but also on sort of
more fundamental ideas about how to
affect people's behavior
um their belief systems uh so for
instance if you insert
uh a lot of chatter about sunshine or
grass or Rivers it makes people want to
go outside but if you insert the phrase
stay at home diseased coveted death it
makes people want to stay inside right
um they've experimented on how this
works on a political level uh by sort of
Market testing how crowds behave when
certain phrases are introduced into
organic conversation
um all the countries do this the
Russians do it and their their program
is modeled after ours
um and I think what you're gonna what
we're gonna find is that a lot of these
companies and there's a you mentioned
the Contracting before that they don't
want to work with Allen well they want
to work at companies like new knowledge
or News Guard there's this huge booming
new industry that everybody knows is
coming it's getting it's only going to
get bigger that's about things like
domestic content uh uh I'm sorry
election Integrity uh foreign
interference
um like extremism watch that that kind
of stuff and there's a lot of money in
this there there was a lot of money
already that's been distributed in
public contracts that are already
searchable there's already a paper trail
connected to the a lot of these
companies so you these aren't just
private efforts these are a lot in many
cases like sort of DOD efforts
um but there is a lot of money here and
it coincides Joe with the political his
sort of Hysteria and machinations that
you're talking about so it's really a
story on multiple levels about how a
political impulse is coinciding with a
practical self sort of financial
interest that is sort of the Eternal
story of Washington a tribute right
Washington is the modern day Rome where
everybody goes to get uh all around the
world to get a tribute paid to them well
they're this is this is a big hunk of
that system is this new sort of digital
information Network
outfits like Hamilton 68 are sort of are
going to be the Forerunner of how things
are done in the future they're not going
to bother with correcting the New York
Times they're going to create uh
narratives before they get to the New
York Times
um and the the whole fabric of reality
is going to be altered uh so that you
have people like that person you dated
I'm sorry to go on about this but this
is exactly what Orwell wrote about it's
this idea of somebody you can have
two contradictory uh thoughts at once
and not be bothered by it the certain
conviction that something is untrue but
the absolute belief that it is at the
same time right that is the that is the
new person that is being created by
these techniques it is something we've
never dealt with before it's a new topic
um that hasn't really been studied and
it's very scary because
they're sort of testing it in real time
with stories like Russia gate I'm sorry
to go on about this but it's I I think I
think people have to understand the
scale of this isn't just a big wrong
story it is is it is something heralding
a new technique for governance
that that that's true Matt but that's
only if you allow yourself to be
enslaved to social media right right
that's true but everybody is the problem
no but that's what's dangerous that is
what's dangerous and and
you know uh
and so you know those
devices you know serve
not just as tracking devices and and
profiling devices but
you know without being overly dramatic a
kind of kind of mind control and they
know it uh and they know how to do it
and they know how to package stuff so it
gives you the right dopamine hits and
it's it's really uh yeah I think you're
right I think it's very
frightening
um I remember when I wrote embar of
Illusion which hit some of these themes
I spent the whole first chapter hanging
out
at Madison Square Garden with
professional wrestling and it reminded
me of exactly that where on the one hand
if you I would interview these people
they all knew it was fake
if you ask them on the other hand they
were screaming and weeping because the
narratives that were created around
these wrestlers and it was I mean you
couldn't make this stuff up I mean it
was you know the guy who'd been evicted
the guy who I mean my favorite was the
guy who just got out of prison and comes
into the arena and is orange
in his arm well they don't actually wear
orange in a prison but in an orange
Guantanamo suit to fight the corrections
off so I mean you can't make this stuff
up but it but it also resonate yeah it
is kind of awesome and uh but it
resonates but and when you said that
about these contradictory that reminded
me exactly of of
that kind of spectacle of professional
wrestling
um because what it does it grips them
emotionally
uh and and it has embodied within it
it's manipulative a kind of emotional
truth and that's what I kind of hear you
saying they're doing absolutely it's
just that they what they've pro
wrestling right was for one audience the
difference with this story is they they
figured out how to do it for these
sophisticated Cosmopolitan Highly
Educated Urban uh class in Western
countries uh who believe themselves
above such pretensions
um but they not only are not I would
actually argue that they may even be
more susceptible to this kind of
behavior
um than the sort of average working
person who has a streak of uh
Independence and that a lot of these
people don't have because they've been
sort of intellectual group thinkers for
their whole lives
um I don't know I'd be curious John to
hear what you think about think about
that but it appears to me that they've
they've figured out how to crack that
audience better than ever before
it sure seems that way
um you know we've been seeing it really
since 2016 and it's become so deeply
ingrained in society that you know I for
one struggle with with uh
with how to get out of it how do we turn
this around I I think that the that the
comparison that you made earlier uh to
that period of of McCarthyism is is an
apt one
how do we turn this around and get out
of it it's going to be difficult
there was only one man then McCarthy
basically who yeah good point Edward
Morrow stood up to him and that guy said
you're having a decency and and that
could have collapsed
where this is much more because it's
because McCarthy went after the the Army
the military the intelligence community
so as soon as he crossed that line he
was finished this is completely
different so everything is now emanating
out of
those centers of power it's it's not at
all like McCarthy it's it's far worse
yeah I mean they've done this overseas
for years I mean you know I mean it's
not anything new but in the end with
every
decaying Empire all of the mechanisms
they use for control migrate back and
and uh and it's uh as things deteriorate
they will reach for every tool they have
and they they know how to use it because
they've used it in all sorts of
countries
uh and and it's it's just it's already
been perfected and tested and it's ready
to go uh so it's it is orwellian it is
really
really dangerous and as the country
continues to disintegrate I mean how
many mass shootings have we had this
month how many people I mean of the
fabric of the society is just being torn
apart and these people are not going to
give up power and they will they will
use everything at their disposal to keep
power and I think that's what we're
watching
yeah I'll just say that the The Twist on
sort of earlier methods of control is
the the technological advance that the
internet allows
um I mean Orwell Orwell predicted in
1984 this idea of this totally immersive
informational experience that
um you know that it works on you at a
level beneath your conscious thinking
but you Chris you bring up the mass
shootings I think they make an
assumption that people are able to
function
without Clarity insanity and Truth
um that I think is incorrect
people can't live without it my strong
belief is that people can't live without
um truth that they will detect it if
this kind of organized falsity and then
it will drive people crazy yeah they'll
detect it but then what was that book
was it by Celeste milosh or you know the
captive mind
so I'm a little short that I can't
remember but but he but what happens is
the society bifurcates so yes you're
right they recognize that it's all lies
but then they Retreat into a kind of
private world of Hedonism and uh and uh
you know this certainly happened under
stalinism and uh you know so so you're
right that that they can see it you're
right that
um
you know and they're all there are
always those great figures so janitsen
which I just taught in the prison uh who
love archipelago but they're always
these figures but when they step out to
speak a truth of course they're uh
they're discredited and and widely
reviled
um uh
uh and
um
uh and what they do is really almost
suicidal I mean it it is you know they
they have to accept that that in order
for them to get up and speak a truth in
this environment is to put their life in
danger they'll do it anyway Oscar Romero
did it in El Salvador
um uh but I I think that in in a climate
of pervasive manipulation and pervasive
intelligence what we may get is that
you know that bifurcation that we saw in
the captive mind where people just
Retreat and of course it's a you know
words of words a pornified culture it's
a culture engrossed and spectacle I mean
just Cicero writes about this at the end
of ancient Rome where everybody which he
invades against but everybody's
emotional life is invested in the arena
uh meanwhile the Roman Republic is
coughing up Nero and Caligula and
everyone else so that's you are you are
right that but but that I I fear that
that's kind of probably the path we're
headed on
that might be a good spot to end it at
unless everyone a very cheerful very
note yeah yeah so we'll go off into the
night
well I just want to I just want to close
I just want to say as a journalist I
think Matt has done you know just
absolutely
you know groundbreaking important
tremendous magnificent work
um and you're going to keep doing it
which means you're going to have less
and less friends so it'll always be one
um but uh it is I I mean I read it and I
was I just thought it was one of the
most important stories I've read maybe
since you know Wikileaks I mean I just
thought it was really really important
yeah
um and so I just want to tell you how
much a lot of us really admire you and
admire what you do well I mean so before
there's not a whole lot to it if you're
in this stuff you know
um so
this was a flukey thing where
um you have a
a a very angry you're not angry a very
um disaffected billionaire uh very
wealthy man who
um
I I think he
felt he had the luxury to do this he's
not a group thinker
um he has a lot of things about him that
people uh may not like but this is a
fluke right this is something that
doesn't normally happen we're a gigantic
major corporation will suddenly start
spilling its guts in public
um and it's a unique thing
um you know how long that will last
isn't really a journalistic issue I
think it's going to be a larger you know
question of whether he can whether his
own race to survive is going to work out
but as long as it does
um you know it's I think that that's
really where this whole this whole
project started was uh with with that
idea which is just interesting I think
well you know but that's often true with
any great investigative work I mean I'm
gonna I was leaked a major Story by
Mossad and shut down a a privately owned
airport owned by Iranians north of
Hamburg because they wanted it shut down
I mean I went to Hamburg I investigated
it it was true everything they gave me
was true
um you know so uh I've I've heard people
attack the source that that's irrelevant
I've been you know I've I've had in
multiple sources from the fmln the CIA
got a big report from the FBI I mean et
cetera et cetera what matters is whether
it's true or it isn't right exactly and
it's our job to which of course all
these people went on the dashboard of
Hamilton 58 68 never did uh but it's our
job to determine whether it's true and
uh and people will feed us crap all the
time but if if we find that it's true we
don't have a right to withhold it from
the public
um that gets into Grand Inquisitor
territory
um it's our job to and I've written
stories as I know you have that have
hurt groups that I care about uh you
know and uh but as Orwell said the only
product we as journalists really have to
sell is our credibility and a lie always
works in the short term but in the long
term it destroys everything that we're
about which is why of course he put in
the plum suppression and Homage to
Catalonia and the Barcelona riots which
he was part of and everything else and
Victor glance in the left wrote him on
you the Victor glance wouldn't publish
it or the ornaments Kettle only sold 600
books in his lifetime but I think that
true yeah yeah yeah it didn't sell at
all it does a great book but it didn't
sell so but you know I think that that
you know that's what you're doing and
and and that's what we have to do
um and it's you know the longer you do
it the more isolated you're going to
become and the more you expose the more
vicious they're going to become because
rather than owning up to the fraud that
they participated in they'll seek as
they have done with Julian to
essentially destroy the messenger so
does it matter as you just said it
doesn't matter the source it's true and
it doesn't even matter if Russia was the
source of the DNC emails they were true
yeah it doesn't well I've always said
you know you can argue that you
shouldn't publish them the badass emails
but you can't then call yourself a
journalist
right exactly something else yeah
and I think that's the other thing that
people
just to close on this there's been a lot
of uproar about how a lot of the Twitter
stories
um you know they're they're framed in a
way that's very pleasing to right-wing
audiences some of them because that's
what we're seeing you know in other
words we're looking at documents most of
what we're seeing is a certain kind of
narrative but I think people have to
understand that it's not just that
there's a layer beneath that that is uh
it kind of goes in all directions
um
but we just got to follow Eric we're
leads
well we'll end it there with the last
word with Matt TYB and we thank you Matt
so much for coming on and sharing all
these insights uh about your story uh
and I think we all agree with Chris that
we admire what you've done here very
much we look forward to more stories
like that and you coming back on CN live
sometime so John kiriakou uh thank you
very much for coming on and giving an
intelligent point of view and
and Chris with your incredible deep
knowledge of many things going from Rome
to uh Bosnia to today we thank you and
again Matt so much and I thank Elizabeth
lost our co-host and Kathy Rogan back in
Sydney Australia our producer so for CN
live this is Joe Laurie saying good
night and we'll see you again soon
goodbye
[Music]
if you are a consumer of Independent
News in the first place you should be
going to is Consortium news and please
do try to support them when you can it
doesn't have its articles behind a
paywall it's free for everyone it's one
of the best news sites out there and
it's been in the business of independent
journalism and adversarial independent
journalism for over two decades I hope
that with the Public's continuing
support of Consortium news it will
continue for a very long time to come
thank you so much